[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: This is CS50, Harvard University's introduction
for the intellectual enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
My name is David Malan, and I actually took this course
myself sophomore year some years ago.
But I almost didn't.
At the time, I was quite uneasy with the idea,
frankly, of taking a computer science course, let alone this course.
And so my freshman year, at least, I really
gravitated toward courses and departments
with which I was much more familiar.
Computer science was well beyond my comfort zone at the time,
and it was really these unfamiliar waters
that I wasn't quite ready to shop, even my first year.
But sophomore year, I finally got up the nerve to come through the door of CS50,
and only because the professor at the time let me take the course pass/fail.
I was that uneasy.
And if only I had known at the time what I now know,
which is that 2/3 of CS50 students have never
taken a computer science course before.
So if you are feeling similarly uneasy with the idea of trying something new,
or even if you have prior background but are
looking to fill in gaps in your knowledge,
or if you're particularly self-taught, realize
you are very much in good company.
And ultimately, what matters in this course
is not so much where you end up relative to your classmates,
but where you end up relative to yourself when you began, which is,
of course, today.
So what, then, is computer science?
And what was it that I was so uneasy with?
Well, I dare say we can describe computer science as this.
It's just the process of solving problems.
And what does it mean to solve a problem?
You've got some input.
And the goal is to get some output, the solution, to that particular problem.
And in between, really, is computer science.
And we'll see what's in this literal black box on the screen
as we begin to fill in some of those blanks.
But when we consider a problem to be solved,
we have to all agree from the get-go, especially if we're using machines,
how are we going to represent these inputs and outputs?
And so one of the first concepts we explore in computer science
is how you represent information itself.
And odds are you probably know coming into this course
that computers only speak what language, so to speak?
AUDIENCE: Binary.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So binary.